Guide to the Betty Trapp Chapman Papers
University of Houston Libraries
Betty Trapp Chapman papers
2003-2009
2005-2007
02/2015-025
Chapman, Betty Trapp
3.00 linear feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
This collection contains research materials, notes and correspondence related to the writing of The Rough Road to Justice: The Journey of Women Lawyers in Texas. The book was commissioned by the State Bar of Texas Committee for Women in the Profession in 2003 under the leadership of Ellen Elkins Grimes and funded in part by a grant from the State Bar Association as well as other donors. Materials are arranged by function, with each series referring to a type of document. Materials are arranged by subject within each series.
Biographical Information:
Betty Trapp Chapman was born on October 18, 1936 in Tupelo, Mississippi to Charles Wilson and Mamie Elizabeth Trapp. She moved to Houston in 1959 for a teaching position in Spring Branch Independent School District. She married Billy Klingman Chapman in 1960; they have two daughters. She has been an independent historian and freelance writer since 1989 and has written several books including; Historic Houston, and The Rough Road of Justice. This collection contains research materials, notes and correspondence related to the writing of The Rough Road to Justice: The Journey of Women Lawyers in Texas.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Genre/Form of Material:
Books; Correspondence; Photographs; Research (document genres)
Geographic Name:
Texas -- History
Personal Name:
Chapman, Betty Trapp
Topical Term:
Lawyers -- History; Women lawyers -- Texas
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains research materials, notes and correspondence related to the writing of The Rough Road to Justice: The Journey of Women Lawyers in Texas. The book was commissioned by the State Bar of Texas Committee for Women in the Profession in 2003 under the leadership of Ellen Elkins Grimes and funded in part by a grant from the State Bar Association as well as other donors. Materials are arranged by function, with each series referring to a type of document. Materials are arranged by subject within each series.
Detailed List of Contents
- Research Notes, id171738
  Scope and Contents
  Notes pertaining to the research and writing of Rough Road to Justice: The Journey of Women Lawyers in Texas.
  - Bibliographical Notes, 2005-2007; id171742 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical Notes, 2005-2007; id171743 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Census Notes, undated; id171744 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Gender Issues Notes, 1994, 1996, 2005-2007; id171745 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - General Notes – Women in Law Part 1, [2004-2007]; id171746 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - General Notes – Women in Law Part 2, 1994, 2001, 2004-2007; id171747 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Individual Women, 1985, 1995, 1997-1998, 2004-2007; id171748 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Judiciary, 1993, 1997-1998, 2004-2007; id171749 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Law School Faculty, 2005-2007; id171750 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Law Schools, 2004-2007; id171751 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Locales, 1995, 2005-2007; id171752 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Minorities, 2006; id171753 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Outline, [2007]; id171754 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Photography Notes, 2005, 2007; id171755 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Publicity, 2005, 2007; id171756 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Publication Process, 2007; id171757 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Search for Women Lawyers (Early), [2005]-2007; id171758 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Statistics, [2005-2007]; id171759 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Texas Procedures, 2005-2007; id171760 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Women Lawyers Association, 2005-2007; id171761 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Outline Notes, id171739
  Research notes organized by chapter.
  - Prologue, 2005-2007; id171770 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Chapter 1, 2005-2007; id171771 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Chapter 2, 1993, 2005-2007; id171772 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Chapter 3, 2007; id171773 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Chapter 4, 1998, 2005-2008; id171776 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Chapter 5-6, 2005-2007; id171778 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Chapter 7, 2005-2007; id171779 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Chapter 8, 1992, 2004-2007; id171780 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Epilogue, 2007; id171782 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Appendices, 2007; id171783 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - End Notes / Information, undated [2007]; id171784 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Manuscript, id171740
  Original Manuscript for Rough Road to Justice: the Journey of Women Lawyers in Texas.
  - Manuscript, 2008; id171786 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Contacts and Correspondence, id171762
  Contacts and Correspondence related to the research and writing of Rough Road to Justice: The Journey of Women Lawyers in Texas.
  - Contacts, 2004-2005; id171788 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence - Businesses, 2005-2006; id171789 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence - Ellen Grimes, 2003-2007; id171790 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence – Government Entities, 2005-2006; id171791 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence – Law Associations, 2005-2007; id171792 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence – Law Schools, 2005-2007; id171793 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence – Photography Rights and Use, 2007; id171794 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence - State Bar Association, 2004-2008; id171795 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence – Texas Women Lawyers, 2005-2009; id171796 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Photographs, id171763
  Photographs of Texas women lawyers collected during research for Rough Road of Justice; The Journey of Women Lawyers in Texas.
  - Photographs, undated, circa 1930s, circa 1970s, and circa 1990s; id171797 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Books, id171768
  Books used in the research and writing of Rough Road to Justice: the Journey of Women Lawyers in Texas.
  - Bowers, Angela The Texas Journal of Women and Law: Women at the University of Texas School of Law: A Call for Action, id171798 (Box 2, Item 1)
  - Chapman, Betty Trapp Rough Road to Justice: The Journey of Women Lawyers in Texas, id171799 (Box 2, Item 2)
  - Dusky, Lorraine Still Unequal: The Shameful Truth about Women and Justice in America, id171800 (Box 2, Item 3)
  - Epstein, Cynthia Fuchs Women in Law, id171801 (Box 2, Item 4)
  - Garza, Hedda Barred from the Bar: A History of Women and the Legal Profession, id171802 (Box 2, Item 5)
  - Jones, Nancy Baker & Winegarten, Ruthe Capitol Women: Texas Female Legislators, 1923-1999, id171804 (Box 3, Item 1)
  - Morello, Karen Berger The Invisible Bar: The Woman Lawyer in America: 1638 to the Present, id171805 (Box 3, Item 2)
  - Payne, Darwin Indomitable Sarah: The Life of Judge Sarah T. Hughes, id171806 (Box 3, Item 3)
  - Raggio, Louise Ballerstedt & Castleberry, Vivian Anderson Texas Tornado: The Life of a Crusader for Women’s Rights and Family Justice, id171807 (Box 3, Item 4)
  - Smith, J. Clay Rebels in Law, id171808 (Box 3, Item 5)
  - Vrato, Elizabeth The Counselors: Conversations with 18 Courageous Women Who Have Changed the World, id171809 (Box 3, Item 6)